Will you tell me what they have?
Yes.
They're starting units in tech.
It's a doozy.
It's fun.
So for units, they have one dreadnought, two carriers, one fighter, two infantry, one space
stock, and two PDS.
Wow.
What a weird choice.
What a ride.
A wild ride.
Great ships.
I mean, literally the best possible ships you could have outside of two war sons in a
dreadnought or whatever.
You have a total of nine capacity to start the game with.
Two bad hooliath, three things to put inside of that capacity, only two of which are infantry.
You don't have enough infantry to do the game round one.
This is our kind of Achilles heel round one is the two infantry.
That's a huge bummer.
Yeah.
Next we'll talk about their starting tech, which is very fun.
They start with four starting tech.
Oh, baby.
Neural motivator, anti-mass deflectors, Sarwin tools, and plasma scoring.
It's all the level zero tech from base game.
It's a really good.
That's a lot of good tech.
Neural motivator and Sarwin tools, two techs you love to just completely start with.
Anti-mass deflectors, a tech you love to have and not have to research.
Plasma scoring, you start with two PDS, something nobody else in the game does, and you have
plasma scoring.
Anybody who's like, I'm going to go attack Joel Norse home system round one.
No, you're absolutely not.
You have three shots from the get.
That's only going to get better given some stuff we have later on in the game.
Obviously, this is a completely ridiculous start.
It's 16 resources worth of stuff for a normal player.
It's a lot of tech that also gives us access to a lot of tech right away.
Not just because we have some abilities, but because I start with the green red and the
yellow, I can get cruiser too.
I can get fighter too.
I can get PDS too.
First round if I want to.
Many of those things are on the table from the get go.
Yeah, so much versatility is the keyword we're going to say versatility today.
It's B for versatility.
Let's talk about their home system.
They are two planet home system, Boo Sugs Bad.
The two planets are called Joel and Nar, of course.
Joel is a one resource, two influence planet.
And Nar is a two resource, three influence planet.
That's five influence.
That's really good.
That's really, really, really good.
It does suck that it's two planets, but beyond that, this is an incredible home system for
especially what we want to do, which is not have to worry about needing too many influence
planets outside of our slice.
The fact that we get basically two command counters for free each round is going to be very
good and lead to a healthy command counter supply all game.
Yeah.
It's yummy.
They're abilities.
The first one is called fragile.
This one's kind of infamous.
Apply minus one to the result of each of your units combat rolls.
That is bad.
Just to make it clear, that's not good.
Now, in space, maybe it's like not the biggest deal in the world.
You can kind of get around it.
You can have lots of HP.
You can mitigate things.
You also have like lots of things that help you in space combat.
Like if you get really good space cannon going, there's lots of things you can do.
But on the ground, that's bad.
Not good to have minus one.
That's where those numbers really, really matter.
It means that on the ground, Jonar has to play the numbers game.
You've got to have more stuff on the ground than your opponent brings or has on the defense.
Yeah.
It's a bit of a ding-dong situation if you guess me.
These next two abilities, I feel like I'm just going to read them back to back because
I feel like they go together.
The first one is called Brilliant.
When you spend a command token to resolve the secondary ability of the technology strategy
card, you may resolve the primary ability instead.
This is paired with Analytical, which is when you research a technology that is not a unit
upgrade technology, you may ignore.
One prerequisite.
Yeah.
That latter half means we can reach any of the two requirement colorful texts from the
get-go.
You can get transit diodes round one.
You could get fleet logistics round one without doing anything.
If you can research two texts, which you can do with Brilliant, you can get lightweight
deflector round one because you can get gravity drive and then research lightweight deflector.
You basically have access to the entire tech tree all game long.
Also giving your start, like we already covered a bunch of upgrades you already qualify for,
and you're very quickly going to get the rest of the colorful texts.
The only tech I would say that is mildly out of your range is War Sons.
War Sons being three red and a single yellow takes some time, and three reds aren't really
something you are like dying to get.
So that's literally the only tech that's not like right there at your fingertips.
Everything else, basically all game long, you can just get any old time you want.
I think we're going to have a lot of fun when we get to the 10th half of this kind of
whole episode.
Wow.
Well, just to get the rest of this useless junk out of the way, let's talk about their
flagship, which is called the JNS high lorum.
I layer him high lorum.
It is a cost eight standard flagship with a two on a six combat value, which of course
is a minus of that.
There's a minus to the six.
Movement one, capacity three, it's got sustained damage and it has a whopper of an ability,
which is when making a combat role for this ship, each result of nine or 10 before applying
modifiers produces two additional hits.
Yeah, that's an incredible ability.
If you've ever seen this flagship in play, you know how quickly that like does a lot of
damage, you know, a nine or a 10, that's a one in five chance of just rolling that.
There's nothing else that modifies it.
It's just the straight up role.
If you get a nine or a 10, you've dealt three hits with that single role.
It's like a whole war son popped off and guess what?
You roll two dice and both of them could be nine or 10.
You can get six hits with a single role entirely possible, not even like that supremely unlikely.
It's two ones on a five, right?
That's pretty nuts.
So this is a great one to just park in your home system and force people to really consider
if your home system is worth taking.
Yeah, I love that this is kind of their only way to punch hard.
I mean, obviously with Jolnar, you're just going to want to have more stuff than the other
person.
But with this flagship, you're just kind of saying like, we're also going to gamble.
Yeah, a little bit.
Yeah, yeah.
Have you heard about gambling?
Yeah, I mean, there's a whole line of thinking with Jolnar that is, I don't have the HP.
I don't actually have the more stuff, but I get to hit more times.
That is basically the flagship and destroyer to line of thinking, which is just like if I
could just maximize the amount of dice that got rolled, hopefully I can carve through your
stuff before you can carve through mine.
And maybe that works.
But again, it is gambling.
All right.
Well, their promise or a note is up next.
It is called research agreement.
This is a very infamous note.
And it reads after the Jolnar player research is a technology that is not a faction technology
in that technology.
And return the scar to the Jolnar player.
Oh boy, this is it.
This is the whole faction in one single component.
If you wanted to nerf Jolnar, you would nerf this component alone and everything else could
just be fine.
Right.
And it would not be a big deal.
But this one's ridiculous.
Contrary to a lot of promise or a notes, this costs Jolnar absolutely nothing.
Which is how promise or a notes should be to be clear.
Everything should come up to right research agreement like standard is the problem with
most promise or a notes.
This is the best promise or a note in the entire game.
And it's going to make you so much money because everybody wants tech because tech is time
locked.
Tech is hard gated on the game of how much gets provided.
Right.
And you get to increase that by a lot.
You get to put way more tech into the game for everybody.
I did also want to note here that that is when after the Jolnar player researches a technology
that is not when you do gain effects like fires of the gashly is gain war sons.
Maul of worlds is gain a tech neither of those proc research agreement.
But lots of other stuff does focused research that's research attack.
So it's not only during the technology strategy Carter that you can sell research agreement.
So this thing is all over the place all game long.
It's the value that it can create for you and others is impossible to imagine the first
time you play them.
And every subsequent game there's just no telling whether you're going to hit the jackpot
or not.
I mean, it's the same thing with tech tempo in general, right?
Like you don't know how much tech you're going to get from action cards.
You don't know how much tech you might find in the agenda phase.
Research agreement is there to say like if we do happen to hit the jackpot, it's going
to be even bigger than you thought it was going to be.
Yeah, this component is I would say certifiably filthy.
I mean, it is a real nasty boy.
This guy.
Yeah, it's gross.
It's real gross.
And guess what?
One of their techs is also pretty gross, pretty gross in its own right?
And go ahead and give me that one.
Yeah.
Let's go right into the faction techs.
The first one up is Erez siphons.
It is a level two yellow tech, meaning it requires two yellow.
Now of course, Jolnar doesn't really care about that.
And you can research it on round one.
And it reads after another player activates a system that contains one or more of your
ships.
Yep.
Gain for trade goods.
Oh boy.
Yeah.
Thank you for noting the ships there.
It's important to gum as Jolnar not only because you got to protect that home system in every
way that you can, but also because of this and for trade goods is a lot of money turns
out.
So it is definitely a deterrent.
People don't just make lazy attempts on you.
You don't get stuff just picked off in the mid game for nothing.
However, in the end game, this doesn't protect you.
This isn't a defense, right?
If people have to come for your home system, they're going to come for your home system.
But you might have enough money as they're on their way to building your home system and
protect yourself.
Who knows?
But it's not the biggest deal in the world.
It's one where if we were to balance things down, maybe I would lower that amount of money
a bit.
Four trade goods is just like awfully steep, especially in what it turns into what obviously
the disgusting nasty TI community has done with this ability and how willing they are
to sort of do it all on purpose.
We've really broken it.
If it were like two trade goods, you wouldn't really see that as much because it wouldn't
be worth its own value.
Because it's four trade goods for one command counter, there's profit in there somewhere,
baby.
You're making...
That's the problem.
The fact that it's four, even if it was three, it would be a little bit better, although
it would still be gross.
I think you're absolutely right that two would be the way to kind of...
I mean, it would still be useful.
You would still get it.
It would be good for Jolnar, right?
And that way it'd be good for Jolnar.
The way it is right now, kind of good for Jolnar and a friend.
Yes, yes.
You can just kind of make endless deals because even if you...
Let's say you're just getting the one out of it.
That's still fine.
You're getting a free trade good and your buddy who's activating you is literally just turning
their command counter into three trade goods, which is not exactly how much it's worth.
I know.
Yeah, whatever.
But it's all...
It's in my head, that's how much it's worth.
Effectively that.
And more importantly, sometimes that really matters.
Sometimes you need the trade goods way more than something else.
Or you're like a faction like Necro where it's like, "I'm swimming in command counters."
Let's turn these into trade goods.
I get way too many of these things.
Yeah, I would always love to just turn one of my command counters.
I mean, literally Necro has a component that will allow them to turn their command counter
into two trade goods.
And this is better than...
Three.
Three is the slam dunk.
Their second faction tech is called Spatial Conduit Cylinder.
It is a level two blue tech and it reads, "You may exhaust this card.
After you activate a system that contains one or more of your units, that system is adjacent
to all other systems that contain one or more of your units during this activation."
Yeah.
This is a cool tech.
And you'll hear people sing its praises.
I'm not going to talk about it very much in this guide, but it's a defensive in nature tech,
right?
It is.
I'm already got some stuff here and I can send anything I want there because everything
is now adjacent to it.
Obviously, it's like incredible for defending mechatal wrecks or defending home.
You just send everything back.
And for a faction who very often in the late game just needs to hold on to like one or two
things, it absolutely has its uses.
But it's not some critical component.
It's definitely a...
We had bonus tech in the game and I can kind of get a little...
You know, I can splurge on some extra techs.
It's very rarely the linchpin of your strategy.
Yeah.
And it's a direct reference to Doom, which you can see this weekend in IMAX and 70 millimeter.
See it on the largest screen that you can people do in part two.
You got to see this movie.
You know, it's...
I don't even like it and I'm going to go see it.
You know what I mean?
Like, that's where I'm at.
We have four commodities.
I'll just toss that out there.
As if we needed it, we make so much money from Eres, Cypher and Research Agreement.
They were like, "How about four commodities, too?"
So it needless to say, "You're rich, okay?
Got it.
Let's talk about the leaders."
It made rich if they had zero commodities.
Exactly.
What I want to say.
All right.
So their first leader, we're going to talk about their agent who is called Dr. Sukaban,
he is the head of medical R&D.
Love it.
And he reads, "When a player spends resources to research, you may exhaust this card to allow
that player to remove any number of their infantry from the game board for each unit removed.
Reduce the resources spent I won."
Yep.
So your infantry builds are comparable to mirror computing.
Is the way to think about this.
Yes.
I can spend one dollar on two infantry and then cash those two infantry in to spend two dollars
on my tech, which means I could kill six infantry for three bucks and buy two tech with
my brilliant ability.
This is actually a great return on the investment and I would like heavily encourage you do this.
The problem you're going to run into is a production capacity issue that you start the game
with.
You have a space dock on a two three planet.
You're building four things round one off of warfare.
And then are you going to spend all of those infantry you need to go take planets on tech?
No.
This is a much better later on in the game ability, especially if you feed into it a little
bit.
Right out the gate, it can be a tricky one to use.
It's even a decent one to sell round one because somebody else might be able to really make
something off of it and you can just like get the money you need for other things.
Although sometimes I do use it on myself literally just to save myself the like one dollar
I need to afford tech or whatever, right?
Right.
This is definitely a flexible ability and adds to our versatility.
It also adds to the like it's sort of in line with e-resiphans where yes, we're kind
of killing a component, but we're killing it for more than it's worth.
You know what I mean?
Right.
In infantry is worth half resources, we're going to kill it for one resource that is used
for a very specific thing.
So I think it really just comes down to like timing, right?
Like timing might not be in your favor and you might not get much value out of this in round
one.
After that, it's pretty easy.
Yeah.
Their commander is called TA Zern who is the deep-rot visionary, whatever that means.
He knows.
The unlock for the commander is own eight technologies and the ability is after you roll dice
for a unit ability.
You may re-roll any of these dice.
What is the unit ability?
Unit ability.
Let's walk down unit ability lane.
Hi, here on your left you have bombardment.
Ah yes, all of your threads can re-roll.
Ooh, over here you have anti-fighter barrage.
Anti-fighter barrage is a ability that can be tricky for a normal destroyer use.
Yours are a little bit better.
If you get destroyer twos, boy are you on easy street with killing fighters.
And finally and most importantly with Jol-N-R, again you started with two pds and as soon
as you get this ability with your plasma scoring, your three space cannon shots do in fact
roll again.
That re-roll is incredible.
It's a very, very big deal, especially since like half of our re-roll abilities or if
we get destroyer two, all of our re-roll abilities are like coin flips, right?
Like essentially close to a coin flip or exactly a coin flip and we get to try the coin flip
twice.
That's very good odds to get hits on all of these things.
This is like the only reason our pds are important to us.
I would even argue in base game it was like yeah you start with two pds but maybe you don't
like freak out about it.
pds too was kind of a strategy with base game Jol-N-R but pok made it like oh yeah, you should
fill your slice up with pds because it's actually a considerable amount of heat an opponent
would have to take in trying to invade your stuff.
This shots, five shots with a re-roll is like nothing to scoff at.
I'm saying, and especially considering we can just throw all the gravaton in there,
blip it late, right?
Who cares?
We just throw it in.
Then yeah, it's a lot, it really cancels out I would say all their weaknesses.
I would say.
They don't have weaknesses.
Again, it's space combat.
The minus one is nothing.
The ground, you don't see this as much, although it's worth noting, you do extra bombardment
or not extra but like your better at bombardment.
The reals help me in that world.
Also, I wanted to note the eight technologies we started with four.
Our goal definitely is to research two every single round.
I'll get ahead of that.
Round one, you just straight up might not be able to afford it given some circumstances,
right?
So you might be behind and in that situation, you're not going to unlock this until
round three but in like a normal, nice kind of affluent Jol-N-R game, you unlock this
round two and now your slice is completely secure.
Yep.
It's honestly a decent reason to take diplomacy if round one is going to be weird for you
because even if you make other people rich, you're going to be the richest.
That's just kind of how it's going to go down.
All right, let's talk about the hero.
So the back of the hero, I've never read the back of the hero before and I wanted to make
sure to get that in there.
Back of the hero is called Rin, a master's legacy, perfected being.
The unlock is the same.
There's always have three scored objectives but then you flip it over to the front which
says genetic memory, brilliance of the high-lar.
I want to read the lore.
I got to read the lore on the board.
Read the lore.
The story.
The young high-lar's gills flared as swirling blackness filled her eyes.
I have a master, she gasped.
Here's the ability.
You dorks, action, or each non-unit upgrade technology you own.
You may replace that technology with any technology of the same color from the deck and purge
the card.
I try myself up on this one because I always like in my brain wanted to say research a technology
and then I'm like, "Oh, so can you get a salt can't you can get whatever tech you want.
You get any colorful tech, right?
Any non-unit upgrade technology you just get it."
So that thing where we were like, "Oh, I could get lightweight deflector round one.
Why?
Why do that?
You can get whatever you want later."
So who cares?
This is also a stall which can be very, very useful.
But yeah, you swap out a bunch of techs.
There will be a whole section later where we give the advice of what do you swap out and
what do you swap in.
But just suffice it to say, "This is, I love this hero.
It is not one of the most powerful abilities in the game, but it is so deliciously appropriate
for Jolnar."
Where just the idea of Jolnar is, I don't really have to worry about tech too much, I kind
of don't even have to think about tech too much because I can make mistakes and halfway
through the game, fix my mistakes and just be fine.
So whatever.
Yes, I can confirm it is delicious.
Then our final component to talk about is of course the mech, which is called the shield
pailing.
Is that right?
You do.
It is a two cost, six combat, sustained damage mech as normal, and the ability reads,
"Your infantry on this planet are not affected by your fragile faction ability."
That's right.
Although notably the mech is.
The mech is on a six.
Which means it actually hits on a seven.
But then your infantry don't hit on a nine.
They do in fact hit on their eights that you want them to have.
So these mechs are in fact great to get out.
You have a reason to do it.
We will talk a little bit about self-assembly routines and how it fits into your toolkit.
In general, I would advise you to get these mechs because not only are mechs good for HP
and dealing hits, but they kind of save your butt on the ground game.
They're very bad at that we already noted.
If anything, the only thing we've said that's bad about this faction is their ground game
and you literally have a mech that basically fixes it, basically puts you on par with everybody
else.
I mean, I wouldn't go so far as to say it puts you on par with everybody else, but if you
have a big ol' stack of infantry, suddenly they're not looking so bad.
But I feel like you do need a bit of a stack because I infantry, I don't hit that hard
anyways.
If everybody else, they just get a mech that hits on a six.
Nas roca is over there with a mech that hits on like two sixes or whatever.
And importantly, too, this is not a mech that you want to stack on a planet, necessarily.
You really would like its ability to spread across multiple.
So you don't get to take advantage on most ground combat of like, "Oh, the first two hits,
I just sustain my two mechs and I keep it full fighting capacity."
Like a single mech being added to your infantry stacks is like very little additional firepower
to contribute.
Whereas a lot of other factions bring in three mechs and do massive damage with those
three mechs and don't take a lot of hits.
Everybody else has a bit more versatility, whereas I would basically argue these mechs
are not very versatile for the Jolnar.
They kind of just need to park on the planets.
You need them to be on.
Yep.
They're a bit finicky in that way.
I will say this is a live question I'm submitting to Dane because you're listening.
The way the ability's written is your infantry on this planet are not affected by your fragile
faction ability.
This planet, does that mean earth?
Because that would actually mean all my infantry then.
Does this planet mean the one that I'm living on?
Because it seems like, so I just feel like there's an issue.
Dane, you wrote it wrong, buddy.
Technically, technically not.
This planet could mean the one I reside on.
You all are the worst.
You do these things.
You do this kind of stuff just to be clear.
Let's give some overview before we cut away for a break.
Tell me about their strength.
They're good.
They're good at a lot.
They're good at kind of everything.
Their start is actually incredible except for that one critical problem.
But you start with a massive leg up on a few critical objectives.
The ones being like, you start with three structures.
One of the objectives is have four structures.
You are like the only person who can score round one off of that structure objective just
by doing this, just by doing the secondary of construction.
You don't have to do anything extra.
And the same is true for tech.
You can do any tech objective round one.
You can get two unit upgrades or you could get two and two colors with no issue on either
direction.
So you're just like good at the early objectives.
You're good at stuff.
You're only the downside being that infantry.
We'll talk about that in problems.
But your economy is also near the top.
You are one of the richest factions in the game because of all the things we've described.
You have an influence rich home.
You have four commodities plus a promise or a note that costs you nothing.
People pay top dollar for twice per round.
Two people pay you top dollar for your promise or a note.
You add any rest, siphons for protection money and you basically should never struggle.
Like economy is not where you should struggle.
Production capacity maybe.
But economy you will not struggle in.
And you can choose to get your strongest defenses online so fast that other players can't
even prioritize hurting you early.
This is not a Nalu and Wynu kind of faction where oh let's just go take advantage of them
early.
No, I can just research PDS 2 round one and actually there's kind of not very much you
can do about me or more importantly I've got things that might make you turn a blind eye
to how decently I'm doing round one.
Maybe you would rather get paid in technology than come mess with me.
I can just pay anybody off pretty much.
There's such a good like illustration of the crab bucket that is while I had a period
because it's like yes sure let's hurt them or stop them or whatever but wouldn't you
rather just be in on it.
You know what I mean?
You really want to stand outside in the cold my friend right come inside and warm yourself
by the fire.
Well let's talk about what their problems actually are though like we said you can get hurt in
round one timings.
And it is mostly a timings issue.
Fixing the two infantry star is not like a hard or even expensive problem to fix.
You start with star ween tools like you can do the secondary warfare spent no money and
fix your problem.
It's that the timing of that warfare is what's going to get in your way.
You will move your carrier out take two planets pop whatever strategy card you have and
then that's it.
You really need warfare to pop.
It's a problem right.
So I would generally say suck it up and have a mediocre round one compared to having a tragic
one because you absolutely could have a tragic round one if for some reason the table wanted
to you have the tools at your disposal to make sure people don't let you have a tragic
round one and you can just flaunt to them listen I'm not going to do that well I'm going
to have a mediocre round one I won't be some scary fish and just do it that way and you
don't have to just like single me out and punish me there's other good factions at this
table I'm not the only thing to worry about so don't just destroy my game on a bad warfare
timing I think that argument is always at your disposal.
I've been on the other side a couple times of the argument where it's I'm playing a weaker
faction in Jolmar wants to gas me up yeah because they figure at the end of the race there's
they're going to cross it before I do yeah which sometimes they're right sometimes they're
wrong yeah but I would always say yes yeah why would I say no to that like if I'm playing
a Sardak that's like this is like the platonic ideal and Jolmar is like I'm maybe going to
have a rough round one unless Sardak helps me out and I can get Sardak tech I'm like yeah
yes yeah okay I mean let's do it you had me at talking to me at all yes like I'm already
sold yeah our home production capacity is a problem and our agent gives us a big reason
to improve it luckily this is a very easy fix get a second space talk at home or get
space on to or hey I got one for you why not both do both of those things and have a killer
game it's actually really great we also are I would say our number one problem and a game
long terms is we can often rely on good speaker order late game to capitalize on our solid
position we kind of need the speaker order to work out for us because we don't have some
other trick up our sleeves our hero is lackluster are you know our tech is face up pretty much
everybody knows what we have access to and none of those techs are going to give us some
wild brand new fresh like aggressive ability we really need the speaker token to do what
we do and that yeah sometimes that just doesn't happen like sometimes you never even had
a choice it's just the speaker token never moved from the other side of the table and
you had to deal with that so I it I would say our biggest fallback is that we are not flashy
we are you know a lot of times we coast into a win but if it's going to be a tricky win
I don't know if you have the gas in the tank I don't know that you can pull off the
craziest stuff like an L one or a no mad or somebody else right framed another way I would
say we're not really a good winslay carousel actions true and that we can maybe enable
others if we see it ahead of time yeah but if we're the ones that I mean think about the
only thing we've isolated as the thing they're bad at invasion yeah you know they're not
good at that yeah and sure bombardment is awesome a lot of home system planets have pds though
yes so well how are we getting around that you know yeah it's tricky I mean one way we
can get around it is war sons but that again we said that's like out it would be a specific
mission to go for that and it's not one we're gonna recommend today but let's before we get
into actual recommendations take a quick little break
[Music]
all right hunter let's talk strategy cards as we tend to do round one we're specifically
thinking about what is actually good for john are here and somewhat similar to the sar
guide that I did recently these are the kind of factions I play which is you're really good
you should probably sandbag a little bit you don't need to like go hard or do anything
while but more importantly that was like definitely the advice for sar john are it's
like you could you could reach for the stars and you really could crash and burn so I
absolutely just advise having like a chill round one that facilitates the deals you want
to make over the like let's go stretch out and do everything that we could possibly do
on the map you're not going to do much on the map and you're you're going to be doing
everything above the table during round one and that's kind of the focus of our strategy
cars is ways to enable around one basically so leadership I'm calling mid tier it's really
not that bad again it's like a safe pick it helps you stall long enough if warfare is going
to give you trouble it also lets you do a bunch of secondaries you can get that construction
out there in addition to doing tech and warfare it's a nice little safe pick if you're fourth
or fifth pick it's you know it's in theory pretty worth taking I would take it over dip
low basically because I think you can come up with the money for everything else and
I would just like to be you know it just safe and stable my question is what would the
stall be as Joel Mar yeah I mean it's not it's it is a burned token is what the stall
is right you don't have to movement units right the alternative sometimes is what you're
stalling for is like warfare did pop but tech is like being weird or something like you're
waiting for gravity drive and in a strange way that can happen and and in some cases like
you're also I would also argue leadership can be used for the secondary a dip low if
it for some reason got picked early or whatever so yeah I mean I think it's a good point to
bring up hunter that it's you know it's it's not a lucrative stall you don't have a trade
ship you don't start with a user destroyer and you are asking everybody to come to you
for research agreement right and that is annoying basically sometimes tech does pop early
though and literally all your stalling for is warfare and in that case you can get gravity
drive and the dread not can get out there and do something if you need it to the dread
not does not need to take a planet it can be your trade ship so it's an option on the
table every once in a while well tell me about dip low dip low I don't like you brought
up a great point earlier of like a reason why it's a thing to do like just go ahead and
get your money who cares about making the table a little bit richer but I don't like
our home system for it we kind of rely on the decent forward system to like make the
most out of this you know I hate to only get like four dollars out of me popping dip
low like that's not really ideal and I think most of the other cards you're gonna have
access to are better for you than dip low but your my life I just put it in the low tier
it can be useful if we're really worried about like affording tech and warfare and the
timings are gonna be weird between those two like a dip low right in between can can have
some use to it but beyond that I think it's just too ugly I'm also known for being very
paranoid about what dip low warfare and tech do to each other and the relationship kind
of everybody the table has and I think Joel and all are loses out on that I think very
often the dip low player can lose out on that relationship sometimes warfare and tech
pop back to back or whatever I just find it gets ugly and we don't have room to
mess around we only have our two infantry like we don't have like time to wait around
for stuff to happen everyone would have to like force themselves to make warfare dip low
and tech happen in a comfortable order and I just think it's ugly so I don't like it
I like it I just want to say for the record I think dip low helps you yeah and I think that
you know at least it depends it depends on the meta yeah you play as you know like I
feel like I play in maybe a friendlier space you know I'm not so antagonistic or hateful
to my opponents and I don't like threaten their livelihood or whatever I kind of just
play the game with them and have a good time but you know what you know there's Europeans
out there and whatever but dip low I think that you do get included in that conversation
with the tech person is generally the tech person that really wants to get something out
of you having dip low right now sometimes I feel like the warfare person you write it
can be a little bit dicey because sometimes the warfare players just like no I just have
this thing I'm doing yeah I'm not actually trying to balance this with anything right
um but I do feel like more often than not you can guess something yeah out of it yeah
but uh politics is next up it's definitely low tier first off we can custodians round
one if we really want to uh if we can buy cruiser two and get a cruiser that's that's
a lot just to be clear but like it's super not impossible those are two cheap things to
do I can spend a token on tech get cruiser two and I can on warfare build a two dollar cruiser
and I can take custodians round one I could also do it in like kind of a myriad of other
little scenarios but all that to say like if I really care about custodians I can just
do it round two so I don't need to do the politics into leadership round two uh but
even more important than that I don't think custodians is incredibly important to Joel
Nars game I think we're stable enough to be able to afford imperial in the mid game or
we're great at stage two's it's just like not where I want to hedge my bets uh and politics
does not help our two infantry problem there's nothing that politics gives us that assists
in our two infantry problem which means you might be doing this like play to get custodians
round one at the cost of actually a very empty slice that I know I've been saying like
you can't be hit hard early but like if you didn't do pds to you could be abused like you
could be taken advantage of and this would be the way to do it is to like open yourself
up by taking custodians I don't really think it's worth it and I think there's other ways
you can get bonus points uh just compared to other strategy cards I'm I'm too focused
on fixing the two infantry problem I mean I agree with you that politics is low tier
I disagree that custodians is not worth taking I think that but I don't think there is
a situation where you shouldn't take a step yeah I don't think I've ever really thought
of I all ordered a different if custodians can like fall into your lap you should do it
if if in those games you know sometimes politics is like fifth pick and it's like politics
or construction yeah okay fine politics whatever you know here um in a I'm trying to get
the most ideal argument I don't think politics is your second or third pick or anything
like that that's what made me need a tier so yeah yeah no I again I completely agree on politics
you shouldn't really be factoring in because like you said wisely custodians round one you're
one of the people that can do that if you're planning on doing custodians you may as well
just take a better strategy card and make custodians happen yeah exactly exactly a construction
I'm labeling as mid tier it's fine uh it's a fine late pick especially it's really the only
situation you're ever getting construction construction is almost never refers pick there's like
two factions in the game they're like yeah yeah just take construction first and you're not
one of those but it definitely uh can help with our bottleneck for round two I wanted to
note here construction does not solve your problem round one because what you're relying on
round one is warfare and warfare is build out of one space stock at home not both okay so
don't take construction thinking it's gonna fix stuff you're still only gonna build four units
round one but going into round two you're like really set up for success you are very much in the clear
and in fact can like really capitalize on things you can build a boatload of infantry round two
immediately cash those in for their like really good value with your agent like it's just really
really good um also getting more pds on the ground uh is great especially if you are choosing to
go for pds to somewhat early it makes your slice incredibly unappetizing so love a space stock at
home and a pds forward with construction yeah I like I like this reasoning it makes a lot of sense
uh last pick situation uh if you are choosing between Diplo and construction you might end up
making a lot of money anyway yeah like exactly and then Diplo is just yeah sure you've made even more
I mean you can never have enough money can you or I don't know can you right uh construction is
allowing you to work on that track that is heavily gated yes exactly yeah the way to think about it
in in the Diplo versus construction argument is Diplo you know if you can really make it all work
that money might help solve your two infantry problem construction doesn't solve your two infantry
problem and I won't argue that it does but it does solve your production capacity problem which
is your other huge kneecap in the game so if you are not going to solve your two infantry problem
and Diplo might not solve it either then you might as well take construction it's kind of the
argument you're gonna have with yourself when your six pick Jolnar is right is Diplo gonna work and
you can work that out right like do the math talk to the people the rule of diplomacy is always
talk to the table before you pick it and work out the deal before you grab Diplo don't blind
grab Diplo ever with any faction I would say like figure out what the plan is going into it and maybe
the plan will work right also construction if you if you choose not to double dock at home which
I don't think you have to know if you have a good forward system like do the double dock forward later
like it's gonna be yeah yeah yeah um but in it and if you don't then you have locked down the
four structure uh objective that comes up later and you are one secondary away from three outside
of very good you basically like in round one said if any structure stuff comes up I am a lot yeah
like there is no way to stop me from getting it yeah yeah we'll talk about structure stuff too
because guess what this is also really good process for getting ready for the stage two which you
might be the only person who can score uh but that only a whole note later uh trade trades high tier
it's always high tier money money is good more importantly though what we already described is you
don't have a trade ship you need people to come to you being the person with trade is a great way
to further incentivize everyone to come towards you they you're gonna sell them research agreement
they want to come to you but when you have the trade you also control how and when that conversation
happens so yeah the money is just like generally great but like getting the jump on all right everybody
I have trade this is when I want to pop it this is what you need to do to get yourself in the camp of
being on the research agreement table this is what I want to research it's just the way to start all
of that and that's your priority round one right outside of fixing the two infantry problem
it's starting the meta game starting the above the table conversations about like how you're managing
all of this money and tech you're gonna have yeah yeah I mean absolutely it is I mean it's a no
brainer most of the time and it's absolutely no brainer if you're gel mar just because if you are
the one holding tech or trade sorry uh the upper limit on how ridiculous this might get right now is
nuts yeah uh warfare warfare I'm listing as high tier it's a bummer that this is the case but we have
a two infantry problem and if we are worried about warfare secondary really getting us just take warfare
we have a bad home doc for the secondary in general we're not like gonna make great inroads uh
relying on the secondary and this just fully lets us control the timing of how we handle our
end one like this is the key to that mediocre round one I was talking about if you have warfare
you're guaranteed things are gonna work out for you there there's almost no way the timings are
gonna get too ugly you're gonna get the money you're gonna build some more infantry at home you'll
probably even build them in time to spend some of them on tech if you really really want to do that
I would say warfare is the way where if your meta is like a little bit less boat floaty and less
talky like if you if you're prepared to have a heads down game warfare is how you have that game
round one right round one is just like I'm just gonna do my own thing and that means warfare is like
I'll just play my solo game and try to sell what I can I think it's the safest pick even if it aims
the lowest like it you know you're not going to accomplish a lot with war because you're absolutely
not double expanding you're like barely getting stuff out there at all you might even run into a
little bit of money timing problems with uh with tech but you can probably talk tech out of that
especially because you're probably offering them research agreement just for the timing honestly
you might not make money off of that one but you get the timing to work out for you so I I think
warfare just kind of works um I I feel a little differently I think that that you know I wish that
I agreed because I feel like we I just live in a world where everybody just takes warfare even though
I've been trying to talk people out of it forever now I know in a world where people didn't
ache warfare for kind of like I think kind of misguided reasons I would probably agree with this 100
percent but I feel like people take it and then they they I I just feel like more often than not
if you are higher up on the speaker order which is traditionally if you're saying hi tier I don't
actually it's this is getting complicated because right now I feel like the the way that warfare is
valued in the abstract is one of the first couple people are gonna take it right first three
we're Jolnar and we're in that position where we can think about warfare we're one one of those first
couple people but if I'm in one of those first couple people and I have access to stuff like
frame and I'm probably like gonna just take trade yeah and think well I'm probably gonna make
warfare work out for me right even something like tech which uh we haven't talked about yet I feel
like is better than warfare because now I'm going after warfare and and if I can just get the
secondary off I don't care about that primary I just want the secondary to happen that's all I care
about yeah yeah I mean I I think it can I think I'm an overly paranoid player in general so I seek
out the path of least resistance uh in round one I'm just so scared um I I think it does like
set you up well to in general I do think it's like a kind of pathetic builds that you're guaranteed
with warfare whereas if you're doing the warfare secondary and the timings do work out like you'll
get a decent build out of it you'll get you know to infantry and like a couple cruisers even or
something I don't know like there's there's ways to do it but when you're doing this method you're
literally getting like four infantry or two infantry a mech and a destroyer or something and you're
like scraping to make the ends meet because the money hasn't come in yet like you're probably building
at home second action is is what the warfare pick right sort of necessitates um and the money just
might not be there yet because everybody hasn't sent out their trade ships or or whatever um so it
absolutely is uglier and I and I don't think it's wrong to like be kind of opposed to it I think
you and I are always like this with warfare and Diplo where I undervalue Diplo and you value it a
little bit higher and then I overvalue warfare and you value it a little bit lower and I think this is
like pretty standard in our strategy guides in general so that conversation is out there I would
also love to live in the world where warfare wasn't picked very often around one and we had factions
like this like Joleneir should be forced to take warfare right that's the world we should
live in exactly yeah what you're trying to argue is the factions that need warfare should be
forced to take it and everyone else should be totally chill with not worrying about it and all of us
to carry your factions should stop thinking about it at all yep yeah I just feel like people it's it's
it is yeah it's very similar to the Diplo problem where you are taking this thing and you're saying
oh I get to do this and it's like well so does everybody else buddy like yeah and and but I would
say the reason I think it's worse is because the warfare primary in round one is worse than the
secondary yep I'm like what is it that you are getting now sometimes you know there is a Christmas
land situation sometimes there's a situation where you're getting custodians around one off of
warfare a critical that's awesome when that happens which I don't see that enough yeah and then I'm
like okay this was totally a time where it made sense but I feel like in general I'm just not seeing
that level of value for it and it lets a lot of people that would be really hurt by not having
it did just kind of skate on by like yeah I should note here warfare is one of the best tickets to
guaranteeing the custodians play and it's not some sort of grab drive lift the token move twice
thing it's the bill that cruiser at home definitely get cruiser two off of track and you've failed
enough infantry as well where you absolutely just get there and you have five infantry or you have
five influence at home like warfare is the ticket to custodians round one right but what I hate
about that play mat is that if you're not double building on round one then you're getting the same
amount of plastic you would have gotten had you secondary yeah you know what I mean like what you're
described I also don't like it just I'm not recommending custodians for jolmar very heavily so I also
am like not super on board with with doing it very much let's finish up by talking about the technology
strategy card itself I'm labeling it as mid tier because yeah it's generally more useful for someone
else to have this card but I do think some of us ti3 veterans holds that sort of mental space for
don't take tech as jolmar that was absolutely the case in third edition you could research more tech
in in my you'd remembering it right I don't know you like there was a big reason to never take
tech in third edition for the addition it's just saving you a token like that's all that it's really
doing good like you get to spend six bucks on two tech no matter what happens it just doesn't matter
so what do you need to have happened with that token is the next big question right instead of doing
the secondary of tech which is why this is just like I don't know yeah maybe sometimes you just do
it because then you get to control the tech timing and everything's fine the bigger problem with any of
this is if you're in that I'm down to my mid tier picks territory techs already been picked what are
we talking about tech is the second first or second pick every single game that you're not in that
position so you just you won't see tech needing to be taken by you almost ever because you either you're
early enough where there's something else you should take or you're late enough that tech already
got taken so it's just not really a consideration you have to think about I like tech a lot two reasons
I like tech a lot is first of all I like being in control of the timing actually that got three reasons
and control the timing yeah is the reason number one reason number two is going after warfare I think
that's great for so many reasons that we've already talked about and the biggest one the number three
is we are selling research agreement twice round one buddy we are making boo kooz bus we can sell it
to the same person you can sell it does open up you you can sell research agreement twice without
taking tech but it is considerably harder you got to like make the neighbors and make the deals happen
you got to be neighbors with the person popping tech when they pop tech it's deeply complicated you
don't have a trade ships that can be hard to do like it's a weird thing to say and yeah with tech
much easier hey two of you get close to me and we'll just make it happen or again you just one
person even just one person like perhaps we're taking tech right so perhaps someone's telling them
twice I see what you're saying well no no it I'm set yeah sell to them twice absolutely but also
because we sell to them before we pop that right and then when we pop it we can sell to him again
but this is the biggest part of it if I am in the position as jolmar to take tech almost always I
am sitting next to the person that took trade yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah that's that part that's
that's just part of it yeah so the fact that I'm next to that person means dude we are a lot on
this dirty deal like 100 percent it is happening yep yeah well uh now that we're done talking about
the tech strategy card let's talk about tech and our philosophy towards it uh you know we we I'm
going I'm choosing to do as much detail as I can here I think in previous guys we've been like
hand wave it's tech I don't know but do whatever but I do think we've gotten more refined in our
thinking of like what's properly like good to do as jolmar and what line of thinking are you having
so the thing I want to leave with in technology is your guiding principle is two in four colors and
three unit upgrades you you should be prioritizing that technically speaking if you research two
tech every single round you kind of barely meet this threshold right right this is uh eight 11 tech
you start with four you need to get seven tech to qualify for both of those stage two's right
will be the only one that qualifies for the two and four colors like that's that's a great position
to be in um yep and you you need to have that so that's your stability that's your old base game
you must get two and two like I would say you must get two and four and three unit upgrades you
should just do that everything else about tech is a wide open playground that you can really kind
of make a mess of and do whatever you want with but you should fall in line with those I would say
there's like occasionally space to get like one more blue or one more yellow before you finished
out the rest of the set right an early light wave might open up some opportunities that you need
round three uh getting erez ciphons and transit diodes is something I've done plenty of times to really
solve some problems in my game so there's plenty of times where you go above the two and four before
you've done the three unit upgrades or whatever but you need to make sure you're like lined up to do
that by around five uh yeah you can literally change whatever techs you want to with your hero though
so that's why it doesn't matter what you get early on as long as you get those things you can't
change out the unit upgrades so what you get as unit upgrades does matter like that's like kind of the
most important consideration is those are what you're gonna have all game everything else technically
doesn't matter really what the logic feeds into though is why you want early economy techs you don't
really need the cool flashy heavy hitters until you're ready to pop them a lot of techs operate in that
quantum data hub node philosophy which is like you use it once to win the game and with Jol-Nar you have
the advantage of waiting to get that tech until the moment before you need it and instead can invest
in all of the other things that just sort of boost you in a bunch of different ways what's hilarious
is you start with like two of them you start with neural and star-ween so there's not like a whole
lot of other economy techs that are critical to get but this is one of our guiding principles is I
can kind of get any tech that really helps me early knowing that I can turn it into a late game tech
later and it's not a big deal so you can make mistakes but more importantly if you're not making
mistakes you can have a great early game and a great late game that are that don't impede on
each other in any way right it's so beautiful the way you get to don't like neural motivator for
instance on the last round right like it's so that you're just like ditching that like anyways
this isn't going to give me anything anymore bye bye yeah it's it's really great uh research agreement
also means with your tech path that if the price is right you'll research whatever the buyer once
again a lot of these techs don't matter and sometimes the most economic decision is whatever's paying you
the most so yeah I will get Duranium in round two because Baronies paying out the wazoo to do it right
um right I would say in that specific instance it better be the wazoo and the whole wazoo if you're
just giving Baronny Duranium but in general like you are an open book when it comes to tech and you
have some things you'd like to get but you don't need much of anything which means anybody coming to
you that wants to pay is front of the line right yeah I mean it's wild how much because of the hero
you can just kind of say whatever yeah you know if they want gravitas yes all right Duran whatever
maybe I can get gravity out but out later I don't care yeah doesn't matter uh I'm not married to any of
this uh so with those sort of ideas aside let's talk about let's highlight some tech that we do in fact
like uh the stuff that kind of matters to us and I think there's early tech and then there's like
mid tech and then post hero tech right there's the stuff we probably want to consider round one
then there's tech we're getting throughout our game and then there's the stuff we transition into
those are those are the three timings so early tech uh gravity drive obviously is maybe a critical
component of your round one you want to get to that equidistant because it's the juiciest thing near
you or even the system next to mechital sometimes gravity drive just is a part of the plan or more
importantly somebody else wants gravity drive and wants to get it off of you so that they can do
something fancier and you're like yeah sure gravity drive sounds good it does help me and it's
gonna help you to we're all all the happier for it uh the same logic applies to hyper metabolism
it's cool that you can get it round one it's the most optimal way to research hyper metabolism
and most importantly someone's probably paying you to get it so you're gonna get an extra few command
counters and get paid to do it I see no problem with that circumstance it's it's not like the best
tech you could get round one but it's pretty good I mean if you're gonna get it you get it round one
right I mean and it it is a sign I think of you having a game that's like we are having a good
economy day you know what's funny to me about hyper metabolism is the whole point is like if we get
it early we get more tokens in total it pays for itself really really well but my argument with
hyper metabolism is you probably will get rid of it with your hero right so you actually won't get
the more tokens than someone who got it in round two right and had it pop round two three and four
you maybe have it rounds one two and three and then swap it out for something else oh you pop the
hero in round three maybe not round three maybe round four but before the round four hyper metabolism
prox right so it's still just three tokens that's that's interesting I'll be interested to hear
that because I thought it was just round five all right I don't think so there is a case for it but
yeah we'll get into it so so those two are our great sales transit diodes is one that I love for
me because guess what are you scared of your infantry two problem solved transit diodes you send
the stuff out you get transit diodes and you send them back home to go sending and you don't need to
get more infantry you can take the planets you need with just to infantry it's like not perfect
but it's one of your solutions it's one of the tools in your kit and also yellow tech a lot of people
don't come to you craving transit diodes but people do want yellow tech there's a few factions out
there that are like I'll pay you for a yellow tech because it's gonna get me men tech closer to
mirror computing or me a con closer to quantum data hub node and so it fits perfectly into the plan
because it's like oh it's gonna help my round one and I'm gonna get like an extra buck of what I
would have gotten from some other sale to help one of these players get get their money out um also
transit diodes is a second yellow that could combo really well with a quick space stock two that I
like a lot like a lot played a couple games where I went early space stock two and they were some of
the breeziest most comfortable Jolnar games I've ever had uh it's a it's a great unit upgrade for
them whether the space talks are in your home system or like a biz free uh or whatever there's it's
it's really good uh pds 2 is another round one worthy tech and it's basically do I have
saw next to me do I have keball next to me do I have a scary neighbor let's just throw the deterrent
up and they will go away for sure um there's a couple factions that might want to get pds to especially
if the unit upgrade thing comes up great pds 2 is like your number one unit upgrade you just
should have in general right and everybody's gonna be pining for two unit upgrades so you'll get paid
to get pds to kind of no matter what but it's also three shots coming out of your home system
with re-rolls by around three maybe even by round two if you buy you know if you get those eight
upgrades or those eight texts by round two you have lots of re-rolls in your whole slice so pds 2
is just great in general yeah pds 2 really locks down your slice or you know or a while yeah I would say
basically until we get to round four I'd say that that deterrent is big enough to last that long
definitely it's it's super duper a early game when people do weird little like let me go snatch this
it's like well you're not gonna snatch anything from jolnar self assembly routines is a red tech you
could get and it's a great one to do early because it's the like the quintessential I'm going to
exchange this for a different tech later right right right it basically has a shelf life and you might
as well toss it out later but you get your four mechs on the board for free especially good round one
if you have a hazardous planet in your slice like doing the secondary warfare to infantry and a mech
then that mech goes and gets a really great explorer on the on the hazardous point like it's great
one so it's absolutely worth getting especially considering you can throw it out later other
factions like yeah I got self assembly and then it kind of stopped paying for itself but for you
it's just like and then I turned it into a salt cannon or durinium armor or a agent oh okay we'll
get there all right cruiser two I'm making a minor mention of we talked about it with custodians
more importantly I would say if two unit upgrades is one of the objectives that you're choosing to do
if the other one is like weirder uh you can do pds 2 and cruiser 2 as your two tech round one and it's
a great solution cruiser two will pay off in later rounds it's it's a good tech to get early if
you're gonna get it at all um so I think it's worth it I don't get it in like a vacuum it's not like
the only one I get but also sometimes you get paid to get it someone else really wants cruiser
two early and it becomes part of that so it's it's lower on this list but it is on the list uh and the
last one is eras siphons I actually don't really like getting it round one but a lot of people do um
the way I would say it's not actually a deterrent right is the problem that's what I don't like about
it is I don't actually keep anybody from doing anything to you they just have to weigh is it worth
giving jolnar four dollars the reason eras siphons is a good early tech is if you're doing
the nasty business right away if you're just getting right into it if it's necro or mentek or soul
or hakan then get eras siphons round one the the bigger reason I don't like eras siphons round one is
nobody's paying you for it they can't crop eras siphons so it's not a sale uh of research agreement
and I don't like that round one I think you need to get paid for all of your tech round one
and then you can get eras siphons round two it's fine it's not a big deal um but right getting it
within the first two rounds is pretty standard yeah yeah I mean I love it whenever you got somebody
that's gonna go dirty with you yeah okay so that's all I have for like early game round one maybe
even kind of round one and two considerations for tech so we're gonna transition into the stuff
that's like I think you should get this like at any old point it's not factoring into the hero
and really this is just the unit upgrade section actually like the the secret here is I'm not
talking about any other techs except for unit upgrades and the ones that I think you should get
and first on my list is dread not to um because my main reasoning for this is we are we still
or I think in the world where we're doing the opposite of Sardak nor math Sardak nor math is my
plus one to combat means the more things I can put that plus one on yeah it's like the best way
to increase my odds so a ton of fighters is good yeah yeah uh and since we have the negative one the
less things we apply that negative one to the kind of less damage we do to our odds so fighter
swarms are good for HP and like we do want HP like we do need to still have fight we always have to
have HP there's no way I have HP yeah but they hit so horribly for us that we really can't rely on
them for any level of hits we need some of our ships to do hits so we need dreads to be as good as they
can possibly be um obviously our combat role like doesn't go with dread too but the movement
is is a big deal we want to just be investing we want to build dreads so we might as well have dread too
right we we should yeah we've only we've only got five dreads right so they need to be able to go
wherever we need them yes I don't know about you but I'm all cowboy probabilistic math at this point
whenever I'm playing Twilight Imperium I don't use the battle calculator don't in general I would
say don't use the battle calculator people it makes you worse at the game you should look at it
and you should be able to figure up in your head around where your average is of a fleet you should
just kind of have that memorized right you're not always gonna hit your average that's how average
is work like it's their outliers yeah but with Jolnar when I'm doing my average math I'm like uh oh
yeah we're not getting any hits right unless there's a dread basically yeah is what is kind of the way
it works out in my head that's not true in actuality yeah we're talking about a negative one
uh on the Jolmar side and then a plus one on the Sardak side yeah uh but still that's a big
difference and yeah you're not you're just not gonna get things going in your favor so if you want
any guaranteed hits we better not be talking about one dread not we'd better be talking about multiple
dreadnoughts if you want a single guaranteed hit right well and also keep in mind too like we need
bombardment like bombardment is a key factor in our ability to fight the ground game right we don't
have a ground game which is why like cruiser two could be cool it's a bunch of bonus range it's like
not a decent it's not that horrible of a role for us but it's one thing with one capacity to bring
like a single infantry like that's just not gonna do it for us right I said earlier cruiser two
was fine if we get it like super duper early and it's way specifically want like unit upgrades round
one or whatever but beyond that consideration cruiser two kind of falls off in like how much it's
really bringing to the table where dread two doesn't like we we want those bombardment roles from
dread two we want dreads to be a part of our fleet ecosystem so let's make sure they have the
range to do it especially if we're gonna get rid of gravity drive in the late game which is
totally a viable option sometimes yeah having dread two and my next recommendation which is carrier
two if those are our unit upgrades we can lose gravity drive and still have fleets that kind of
get where we need them to be if you know if we're willing to restrict ourselves that much um
carrier two is also good because again fighters aren't perfect for us but we do need to bring more
ground forces to fights than other people so the bonus capacity on carrier two is absolutely
helpful in getting stuff to the ground game so right carrier two always a great unit upgrade and
continues to be really good for jolnar yeah so cowboy math so how many fighters do you need to have
before cowboy would tell you that you might get a hit ten ten fighters uh I thought that they
pure jolnar well actually that is sort of my point I guess jolnar it's ten yeah right everybody
else it's five yeah right like that's how bad it is right it's really bad that at those numbers like
at where fighters hit at minus one is at your odds you've really gutted yourself that's that's
exactly the problem whereas losing one value on our dread is like a really minimal percentage loss
and carrier bringing more ground forces to endure the fight uh is is very very important and then
again I'll just reharp that gravity drive point of like the bonus range we could even potentially
get rid of gravity drive whatever um right those two are also up there because we're almost definitely
getting a second blue like we we're almost definitely getting gravity drive in most games it's
just it just comes up like you even in games where I'm like I'm gonna not do gravity drive this game
there became a reason where within the first two rounds I needed to get it half the time it is
because someone else is like can I buy research agreement and you get gravity drive and you're like
well I'm not gonna pass that up I I might as well it's a good tech for me to have so we're thinking
we don't have the tech skip on our unit upgrades like one of the earliest things we're gonna have is
two blue and then one of all the other colors so I think generally speaking that's why dread two and
carrier two are also up there as opposed to infantry two destroyer to all of that stuff like we
we qualify for these right away this is where I'll also bring up space talk to it's very common
that we get our second yellow right away whether it be eras hyphens or transdios which means we do
qualify for space talk to it's sitting right there we'd really like to have three unit upgrades
maybe you don't go pds to in a game and you go space talk to instead and you you just like really
focus on production capacity I think this is a strategy that works great for Jolnar again especially
because our rule of thumb is we have to bring more stuff than other people to fight right because
it's not gonna hit us off and we just need straight up more of it so we really have to fix our production
capacity problem and space talk to is like a really good ticket to that yeah I mean it makes sense
it solves your problem and you have so much tech that getting space talk to is not a weird thing
let me ask you though why why not fighter two what's what is why is fighter two not included in this
discussion you know I think it's a fair question I I never seem to make time for it because the
like I mean honestly usually the upgrades are the thing I'm saving for last I fill out the two
in four colors and then I start getting upgrades to prep for the late game and you know you get your two
unit upgrades like right away and then the third one you're sort of squeezing in is how it always
feels to me like you're just sort of like I'm crossing the finish line with that third unit upgrade
and I just think fighter two is like fourth in line or something because it's because really
it's it's some bonus movement right those fighters can like all kind of become a part of the fight
but right the fighter two thing that is like you don't need to have capacity that's not a real thing
right for Nalu their fleet supply thing being half now these fighters like have this kind of
relevance beyond our capacity sometimes but with fighter two you are still generally in like a
fighting scenario you are using fighters that are within capacity because you're filling up all
of your fleet supply with carriers and dreadnoughts right so that part of fighter two kind of doesn't
exist to me and then we're just putting our fighters like on par with everybody else which isn't
you know that's that's fine that's good it's doubling our odds right of of scoring hits with
fighters that's a pretty amazing thing but yeah I just feel like I've not generally found the space
for it the other thing that like puts space stock two above it for me personally is I find value in
like really farming out that agent where it's like yeah I spend only infantry like if I get
space stock two I'm never spending another dollar on tech I'm spending six infantry and then a
medial planishing those infantry with three bucks worth of infantry like it's right it's a good
little ecosystem that lets me spend more on other stuff I can just start hoarding trade goods for
the late game I don't see what fighter two does to my toolkit more than these other texts do
yeah I mean for me I feel like it allows you another path which is you kind of go fighter swarm yeah
um it it also I'm getting a vibe from you that maybe you don't research sling relay that much
whenever you play Jolnar because I'm a big sling relay guy yeah yeah so for me
Ling relay makes it so that that's how we get all the capital ships out right and all of the
space stock capacity is just for fighters and infantry that's all I use that for so in that scenario
space stock two isn't really much of a factor like right because it as long as I'm getting the extra
use case at a sling relay I mean maybe a forward dock is a factor but space stock two is not
solving a problem for me if I get sling relay but if you're going without sling relay then yeah
I think space stock two does make sense and then yeah you're probably right you don't have enough
time to throw fighter two into the mix I just want to make make a little argument for it and I
think there's an argument there for it I do also I think it's just that my line of thinking is that
these fighters are primarily literally just the HP shield and mm-hmm even doubling their odds
is still pretty bad odds for getting hits whereas my fourth and final like upgrade I would recommend
is destroyer two and I'd probably get destroyer two before I'd get fighter two as well because
yeah I'm gonna still just sort of like have this rough HP problem but if it's HP versus HP
the quickest way to make that a fair fight is for my AFB to roll twice on a diet on a coin flip right
well yeah so this is how I play it is the third unit upgrade is either destroyer two or fighter
two depending on the opponents destroyer two is not always useful there's lots of factions where
destroyer two doesn't really do anything to their deal yeah I I didn't end up getting destroyer
two in the games I played like in the last couple months as Jonar I never ended up getting destroyer
two I have done it before I think it's a great tech for them but it is absolutely like a situational
kind of thing to go for but everybody who's ever gotten it in the situations where it's useful
will tell you holy crap it's like the best tech in the game for Jonar like it's incredible when it
is relevant basically right of course okay so that's all of my mid game techs my unit upgrades
that I think are like really worth it the next section here in tech is to talk about that hero and
what we're getting rid of and what we want to get those are the two things I've split it up into
because it's not always like a one-to-one thing there's stuff you want to get the stuff you're probably
okay with losing so first let's talk about what we are okay with giving up the first thing I want
to know when we're doing this that's my big question when does this happen I think I listen where did
I listen to this guy it's it is coming up it's here I'll say it right now I I think
I've made a case for it in round four in more games than I would have thought I think it's
most at home in a final round right because you just you don't need the stuff to do tricky things
until the end and it's a stall and like there's not there's certainly not a need to do it sooner
except for the way a Jonar game can be paced out is you are kind of a target at this point in the game
or whatever and sometimes in round four you need to be making some of your moves not aggressive moves
sometimes it's pulling stuff back from what you did in round three or whatever but sometimes you
need to get your stuff ready to go in round four I also one of my other games was just that I literally
had a proven endurance and round four was seemingly the one people were going to stall less hard on
so I had to pop it that round because it was like I stall I am going to get bio stems and
sling relay off my hero that's two more stalled like I just went for that that route and I in
multiple games I've come up with a reason to do it in round four even though I do think you're
aiming for round five like I absolutely agree with the logic that you're mostly thinking about
it's not like a haqon hero where it's like do it as early as you can to get the stuff out there
yes it's you you you can absolutely wait on things I would I would argue I just would struggle to
pop it before I mean if it's for a point it's for a point and if you're using a component for a point
you're doing it correct like if there if you were if if there's no other way to score that point
besides you using that component yeah there's no arguing with that that is absolutely bullet proof
but I want I'm the thing that I would think about with it is until you know what the stage two is
right you don't feel like you have enough information to actually go off of what kind of final
round it's going to be right and what you are going to need with the big question of course the most
obvious thing would be like light wave yeah but there's a lot of other things that are less obvious
that I feel like are also fully informed by the stage two right I think that's a really good
point of like like a decision point to is because you can have Joan R games where you're not
necessarily leaning to the stage two you found a bonus point seed came up right something like
everybody got a bonus point or there's any number of factors you did the round three imperial
mechatal point or something and if you're in that situation round four might be the like I got to
get my stuff ready to go because I'm gonna get punched in round five like I need to prepare for that
whereas yeah of course if you're if your tempo is no stage two then it doesn't matter but I agree
with your tempo is stage two that's when you're like you should wait until you know what the heck
that is because also functionally there's no difference really in popping your hero at the end of
round four and the beginning around five except for knowing that stage two right like beyond anything
else you haven't accomplished anything by doing it at the end of round four and you're probably not
doing it like early round four that would be pretty weird to like make that the point you do it in
xbook example even further than what I was saying before with lightweight I think even the more
obvious point is anti-mast deflectors yeah so obviously would love to throw anti-mast
deflectors away but all the sudden empty space comes up at the stage two right and we've thrown it
away well that's now you are fully dependent on tech being taken what are you gonna take it yourself
now you score on the seven your whole game is ruined off that decision for sure yeah it's funny
too because that's my first one to talk about is you you're always at least thinking about getting
rid of anti-mast. Of course why wouldn't you get rid of it yeah you don't need it if it's not a
asteroid field game it's useless you don't you don't want to have it yeah yeah yeah gravity drive is
another one you might consider giving up and the only reason I even say this it feels weird to
give up gravity drive but like when the tradeoff is fleet logistics and lightweight and you haven't
like you didn't go further into blue and I've had plenty of games where I did not go three deep
in the blue I I went three deep into yellow two deep into everything else and I'm literally
just swapping out my two blues then and I want I want sling and lightweight or I want three logistics
and lightweight or something and that's when it is okay to get rid of gravity drive especially if
you did the right upgrades that it's not punishing you by by you know doing that but I definitely don't
do gravity drive automatically there are there are certainly games where that's not going to be the
right choice to get rid of that neural motivator obviously especially in round five if you're
doing around five get rid of neural motivator what are you doing the problem with neural motivator
uh we'll talk about in the what are you gonna get what green tech are you getting instead there's
like only a couple options kind of and both of them are also just like I mean sure you get that I guess
because you just don't need neural motivator there's no reason not to um right SIR we we researched
it with the intent of getting rid of it you are going to get rid of self assembly routines you don't
care about the trade good ability on your yes you have plenty of trade goods at this point you got
the value out of it you already made the money you did it you you got four free mechs on the board
and now it's time to cash that puppy in um those are the main things I think about getting rid of you
could get rid of star ween tools uh but more importantly yellow is not something I end up trading out
in the end game the only thing I could do is swap out scan link or a swap out star ween tools for
scan link if I'm doing any sort of uh fragment farming or something like that right if I if I'm doing
the same goes for like anti-mass to just get dt like if we're going gambling right let's go gambling
that's something great to do with the hero is to switch into the gambling thing I'm not really
talking about any of those in this but I should throw it out there that you you can switch to that but
beyond that with yellow like I usually end the game with star ween uh e-res ciphons and transit
diodes I don't know what other yellow tech I could want predictive I suppose you you should throw out
uh star ween and get predictive that's probably the thing you should just go ahead and do
yeah I mean especially if it's if it's a blind pick if you haven't seen the stage two yeah
predictive I feel like probably I mean it's gonna actually line up with some objectives yeah
where star ween does not so so star ween doesn't really provide you anything anymore right so I mean
it's worth throwing it away just to have something yeah I mean even gravitan might be well of it you
know yeah honestly when I write this outline I just forgot to think about yellow tech so there's no
yellow tech written on here at all so this this is alive me realizing oh yeah I didn't talk about
star ween tools at all in this outline time to talk about it uh so what do we want to get though
what's what are we after uh we basically already talked about blue tech lightweight definitely one
um getting rid of neural motivator and one of our blue techs bio stim sling relay sounds great
honestly in a lot of situations especially style potential just straight up stall potential to hold
out your final round moves until the last possible minute especially if you're doing your hero like
that is three baked in actions that you don't have to do other stuff during that sounds great to me
in so many situations um and that's probably my number one green tech to swap for uh you might also
if you got hyper metabolism uh because somebody had you researched it or whatever and it's probably just
it's probably the green tech you got after uh starting with neural motivator you should just swap
that puppy out for x89 bacterial weapon I don't know that you're gonna use x89 bacterial weapon but
I don't know what other green tech to recommend to you and that one might come up especially though
if you've got war sons if for some reason you did get war sons in your game uh hey baby you're
gonna want to get x89 bacterial weapon that's gonna be really cool uh that you have those two
techs in conjunction with each other also bio stems might go with predictive so I mean predictive
and gravitants so if you end up with predictive gravitant and sling that's a lot of options for like
how you might utilize bio stems and I like the versatility even though sling relays the most
obvious use case because it's an action right but but the others are at least keeping your opponents
on their toes about how to do you you at least get to do with slice and then immediately bio stems
it and then you're just like and now I can still do whatever I want with these other you know
these other things right it's all all my stuff is on the menu basically um after that there's a big
question about red tech honestly um and I go a lot of different directions with red tech um I didn't
write duranium on this outline that's wrong yeah like you should consider duranium you have a lot
you have a bunch of dredds duranium is gonna be great for you but also assault cannon is like a very
good tech and it's not too hard to make sure you have three ships like in each of your systems
I am a weird little freak and I find myself getting mage in defense grid um but I was kind of
running the numbers even prepping this guide and I don't think mage in you know works out by logic
with mage in is we're bad on the ground game well one thing we can do is uh we're talking about
mage in defense grid omega which uh means we get to like score a hit like before the combat even
starts right they got it they got to assign a hit um but the mass is wrong here because a you've
already probably fire if if they're coming into territory with structures you've already fired pds
at their ships and at their incoming ground forces uh mage in starts to feel like win more on that
side of the defenses whereas what you really needed was assault cannon to take care either they
have to bring a dummy destroyer or they don't know how to get around your assault cannon on the defense
like if we're talking about holding on to a win if all of my critical systems have three capital
ships in them my opponent has to figure out how to deal with that it's of course right possible to
figure out but some factions can completely struggle to like get the right fleet composition to come
into an assault cannon ready thing and the same goes for me on the offense is I I can catch someone
off guard and snipe a carrier sometimes it's an offensive defense you just go sniping some ships
and then they can't find a way to retaliate back against you so it's really hard for me not to make
assault cannon like the number one recommendation even above deraian because I I just find there to be
or even more versatility in it whereas deraian is definitely the like
that's some hp if we're talking about needing hp right to just sort of survive fights that is that
and we got that's the way to do it and we have dread to just like it's definitely investing in the dread
army if I were willing to get rid of plasma scoring I would say get both but I'm not like you need
to keep plasma scoring in no way would we recommend get rid of plasma scoring it's way too important
to like all of the things in your toolkit but to just throw out self assembly routines like I don't
think deraian and assault cannon is better than one of those two in plasma scoring although I don't
know check your board I think I think you could think about I don't think plasma scoring is off I mean
because yes it's an extra die and it's a reroll die but there's gonna be a lot of games where
that's not gonna be very relevant right like think about plasma versus like like let's say you're
playing a defensive game because you're winning which might be likely you want to you want to get rid
of plasma in exchange for both assault cannon and deraian and then change out one of your yellows
for gravitan that's a lot more punch really the gravitan is like replacing plasma basically
and that's the duration you can't yeah and deraian like why choose like I mean assault cannon if you
have the right setup assault cannon is a guaranteed hit whereas plasma scoring is a 25% chance at a
hit or whatever the right equals yeah but it just depends because yeah the it depends on what you
know I mean if you have to bombard the last ground force then yeah you gotta be plasma yeah
so it just depends on on the exact situation but I feel like those are kind of the like metrics
yeah I mean I'll never forget the prelims game last year that I lost uh that where I had gravitan
and it almost saved me but then there was like something getting messed up and you know we just like
because I'm a cool guy we were able to just like we went all the way through the action but then we
completely wound it all the way back so that the other player could win uh basically actually
wasn't even that player was another person one and I think they would have won regardless of what
happened with that but you know because I'm a cool guy when there was a huge mistake happened
let's just wind it all back you know what I mean like oh let's let's wind it 15 minutes back
that's cool we could start the whole game over I think yeah yeah yeah some people play different some
people will be like oh you messed up and we're just gonna live with this because I like that
and no winding back at all and you know what how about that be sudden like suddenly no wind back
and I have to just be like that's cool you know because whatever you all want you know I'm just stuck
in this little hole with you all you know and whatever you want I just I just give it to you
you know just have it you know check out our YouTube uh sometimes
all right let's talk about uh the meta trading that's enough attack you get it you get how tech
works we've done you get it it's all the tech whatever ones you want uh-huh so uh in our trade game
obviously this whole time the focus has been on research agreement uh this thing is like basically
worth eight dollars around that's maybe being generous I don't know it's at least like six bucks
around is the math that a lot of people will talk about they'll say you can definitely sell research
agreement for three bucks right you for pop which means the six bucks you spend on tech should be
paid for by the two people you're sharing that tech with and so tech for you in theory is free right
you're just getting free tech uh for the cost of a command counter or whatever um you you you should
be trying to get it out there I think the biggest thing to think about though at a higher level which
you'll know is exactly who is getting that tech and when and how and what you know how are you keeping
things balanced I don't like to buff up like one person the and especially the factions that can
most reliably afford tech all the time are not the ones you need to be boosting up to that degree
like we're talking about like a con a con does not need to receive that many bonus techs they don't
need eight techs uh you know they don't need every single research agreement all game long or like
more than half of them that's way too good for like a faction like a con or soul or whatever a lot of
the factions that can afford it why not boost up sardak and bear any a little bit and these other
factions that are like pining for it and you keep everything on like an even keel you keep the
entanglement alive and you make everybody happy so that there's not somebody who's just like really
pissed off that they never got research agreement because you just kept it in soul's hands all game
long mm-hmm yeah I mean this is tough because this is a little more an opinion on like meta style you
know obviously if you're doing like I mean especially because you you called out a con so like yeah
I guess you're not doing like Matt is anti-cap fish there's no catfish in Matt's world uh if this
this is a style choice this is not it is like I actually grew Matt in this case I'm kind of the
same way I don't really like to go right or die with somebody um because I can't trust anybody I
mean there's no one in this world that I can trust you know not even my own parents could I
write or die with in a game of ti at this point um and that's mostly because they don't know how to play
but even if they didn't know how to play they'd be like haha I tricked honor everyone saw and
you know and then they become this legend on this weird shadow discord that I don't know about
where a bunch of like weird people say mean stuff but then I do hear about it actually that's what
I want all the people to know is I actually do hear about all that where's a bowl like you want
to know that you have a mole all of the shadow discord have a mole and all of your stuff is getting
to me alright I hear about all of it uh you dorks uh here's my other point though to this is like oh we
can say right or die but realistically like when we're doing these sales and it's turning into an
auction right of who's actually going to get it the the rich faction they're only paying you like
a dollar more is is the way I think about it like yeah I can make one dollar less and not boost someone
out of my control because especially it's less than just like a a right or die kind of thing to me
it's like I'm in maybe it's because I play with like RY's too much or something but the logic in a lot
of my games is if you boat float too hard with one other person the rest of the table goes then I don't
I could care less what happens in this game it's your it's explicitly your problem to fix like
Jolnar you made Hakan a problem and you can just let Hakan win or you have to stop them we are not
going to take place like we're not going to take part in the win slay so that's why I've I don't do
like hard boat float hard ride or die I do table boat float like let's keep ever but that's what
the sugar does that's what I see the sugar do and and I'm gonna follow the sugars lead because they
are really good at this board game turns out well they quit so I mean how good are they yeah I mean
like Quitter's never know now we're in charge you know what I mean like the sugar's rain is over you
know it's our game now but more important than money if it isn't just about dollars it's about
favors if tech objectives are out your research agreement helps people score objectives so what do
you need in exchange you should be able to score easy stuff to because you're handing out points
is the way I would think about it you it's it's not always as explicit as that but if it's just money
you can take my point above I don't just take one dollar more to boost someone up but if it's for
points if it's for like good favors and and more important things like you should do the things
that are like really good for board position really good for or tempo and all of that stuff you know
I will boat float a bit more in that regard I suppose you know everybody's always talking about how
Cole Whirlies out there making these games that are like explaining various complicated historical
situations and how evil they are but then we're over here with our stupid science fiction game
being like if you have money try to get money but also try to get people to just do stuff for you
I mean aren't we sort of covering it here isn't it clear what the root of the various problems are
do we have to go so deep in order to explain it with capital if you have some I mean what more do you
really do we really need to go and zoom in that type can't we see the problem here uh this is
especially true in round one I would take things working out for me round one over raw money right
this is where we're talking about the like hey how about you just give the person with warfare
research agreement and then they do yeah they do the timing you need and maybe they pay you like a
dollar on top of that or maybe not maybe it's just straight up here's a research agreement don't
mess with me let's make this easy use the agreement to what is it called lobby or like kind of your say
about something structural that's gonna happen in the game I get it I get it yeah yeah yeah yeah it's
a good it's not an evil faction right it's not evil it's not yeah there's hey there's good guys
and bad guys okay they all lobby yeah uh speaking of don't forget about your pds especially if you
get pds to maybe you aren't charging to not fire all the time but it's important that your neighbors
know how nice you are for not firing so that they can repay that kindness also yeah yeah you know
just sort of like horde weapons of mass destruction so that you can tell everybody else not to use
their weapons of mass destruction yes yes yeah my buddy meal and Patel has a really good joke about
this uh look him up on instagram and tiktok meal and patel one of the funniest people oh we haven't
talked about our alliance at all yet our alliance is quite desirable I would say it applies to anti
fighter barrage space cannon and bombardment there's a lot of factions that that covers right like
there are lots of factions that those three things factor into stuff that they're doing so you have like
kind of a decent number of people you can try to get your alliance to uh I have some beautiful
preerata here from the tech meister himself jadeem Jedi uh did all kinds of writing up but I especially
buddy I especially liked jadeem jedi's uh relationship sort of guide here here here's a bunch of
think ways to think about some of the factions in the game and I think a lot of these especially
applied to the alliance but are in general like relationship things to think about but I just I
like this list of stuff to consider as jolnar uh the nomad by the cavalry early and often with your
commander a lowly carrier becomes a considerable force again remember the cavalry has anti fighter
barrage that you're gonna reroll on and it's gonna be like a decent role if they get cavalry too
like it's really good you can alliance swap with nomad and it's great for both sides you get the
flagship they're gonna get your your commander will also or your alliance will improve their
flagships anti fighter barrage roles they'll they'll do very very well with this they're a wonderful
alliance swap uh I don't know if that swap is completely I think rarely does jolnar get a
completely equitable swap I think a lot of times they're like in in a number of ways doing a little
bit more for the other person or do you think it's the other way around I think free flagship is
even better I think free flagship is a little bit better yeah it might depend on what hair it might
depend on what the nomads hero parade is going to entail I suppose yeah if they already have
memorial to or not yeah uh also obviously the necro if they are your neighbor you might as well
plan to make each other rich rather than fight it uh they can also they can pick up your siphons you
both activate each other remember how we talked about it's a net gain this is like the classic combo
both of you just activate each other back and forth those four bucks three of which get
spent to replace the counter you made a dollar you just make a dollar we should just get like we
just need like in like we just need day into like right yeah just like in with ink like it doesn't
matter how he writes it and we just indeed his handwriting saying that you just can't do that
anymore like and it's not even like explained why it just says necro can't get e-res done yeah
done just done all that yeah uh argent flight is another classic uh commander swap it's great for
both of you you're also one of the few factions that actually want to buy their promissory note their
promissory note adds uh one more role for a combat it's like oh it's like a single round of uh an
extra plasma scoring that's pretty good for you um this is another situation where definitely
argent gets more out of having a real line for sure but if you can keep them on the horn for like
let's do an alliance swap and you give me your faction promissory note pretty often then we'll be fine
if I get a bunch of bonus rolls out of this swap then maybe we're fine um if I was argent
I'd be so chill with that I'd be like yeah you can do your commander so bad yeah yeah yeah I'll I'll
give it to you whatever and I would hold my word too I wouldn't I would just it would return to my hand
and I would instantly trade it back to them at the first opportunity like it's just an ability in
the jolmar really uh hakan is the classic catfish thing trade convoys is great I think it's crazy for
jadeem to bring this one up I uh as hakan I don't I would I don't ever sell trade convoys to jolmar
I maybe that's being not being catfish enough or being boat floating enough I hate the idea of jolmar
not needing my approval to trade stuff around the table like I want them to come through me to do
research agreement stuff so I don't like giving trade convoys from the hakan perspective but yeah
if you're jolmar try to get it see if they do it uh I just think it's I think that's a terrible idea
I think that makes it way too easy on jolmar to do stuff they already do really disgusting um well
I think I I can see it maybe if hakan is going war sons like if it's gonna be war sons hakan the idea
of my bumbumb well I don't know actually is that kind of win more do I really need to reroll my
war son apartment generally speaking yeah I I think the classic catfish is just that it's money
for tech all game long like that's like the main combo um it is worth noting too though that uh tech
action cards research agreement a bunch of these ones where you research a tech
hakan is like generally speaking better served giving those to you and both of you getting the tech
and then there being some sort of payment kind of within that but hakan getting tech action cards
and then just using it on themself isn't always better when they could make a dime off of that like
they they can just sell you that action card and you both get tech and you you know all this stuff
works out so that's that's what I like the delicious little combo um the mahawk is an interesting
relationship I would say this is not some sort of like beautiful combo uh jadeem says try to buy
sector of dominion from them because you need win slay defense I love that point just in general
if mahawk's in the game try to get that try to get that promise or you know also their hero makes
defending space a huge problem so make sure you have ground forces on your home system plan it's
this is less a how do you deal with mahawk and more a what do you need to think about when mahawk
is in the game and that's what you have lost the space game even more than you already were you need to
this if mahawk's in the game like this is where I would be like get yourself space stock to
and farm infantry and max like crazy and get them on all of your plan everywhere you just need
stuff everywhere uh to project yourself um nalu is another consideration offer research agreement
for their agent zeu uh you can usually find good places to build extra or score control objective
or win slay someone etc i would also say nalu is like very much pining for research agreement they
start with a kind of awkward tech star and would love to get like a jump on things i almost argue
buddying up too much with nalu those way too many balls in their court like that that's a lot
better for nalu i would say because in the end zeu yeah like to say who is zeu is really good
yeah well i mean i feel like there's no way you're getting it round one because nalu has to use
zeu for themselves round one right after round one if nalu is giving use zeu that's you're getting
two things you're getting to use zeu and also nalu is not using it on the right so it's kind of a win
both way yeah yeah it's true uh soul offering research agreement for multiple uses three to four
of military support is great for both sides definitely agree here like the infantry is our concern
a single research agreement for like four yeah it's that's a great trade off um your agent really
wants more infantry and this is one of the easiest ways to pay for double tech um yeah just in general
getting military support off a soul should be a focus of john ours strategy alongside soul um and
the last one here just says um always punch the winoo uh great no love that no notes uh very good
i like that jadeem's thing like it was good advice but it also kind of there i if you if you had
if you listened with a close ear i you could hear a little propaganda a little a little fish based
propaganda i'm not gonna call out all the points where it happened there's a few points where i
i noticed a little bit of fake news happening in there uh this is a problem for everybody everybody
benefits from this and it's totally equitable uh let's talk about the end game uh late game scoring
etc one important uh no this is where i put in the thing uh where i said round four is usually good for
the hero we had this discussion though round five is generally what you're actually aiming for it
really just depends on like what you're doing one of my points though with this is you're not
waiting on the hero with some intent to blind side the table with your mysterious tech picks
everybody knows what you're gonna get like don't think of it that way what you're waiting for is again
that stage two consideration you're not surprising anyone by getting lightweight in round five who knew
uh the objectives are where we become an overpowered faction though this is this is where we make
our money uh and and cash in games we are the second best in the game at tech objectives and
occasionally we're even better than necro but necro can outpace you uh in tech plenty often half
of the structure objectives are a complete cakewalk i'm talking about the ones that are just have x
number of structures you start with almost half of the stage two you start with three structures and
you only need seven for the final uh for that stage two the one where it's have them on planets
outside of your home you're obviously kind of on an even keel with everybody else but you have a lot
of reasons to invest in structures throughout the game so you might as well lean into that advantage and
lock that uh public objective up like that means four stage twos that a lot of people look at and go
well that's not happening like literally impossible because there's not enough time left in the game
all of the tech and all of the structure objectives they can just be completely in your grasp uh
where nobody else can do anything about them um and a lot of times with the structure ones they
protect themselves oh we got to knock two structures off a jolnar because they have nine too bad they're
all in like four total systems and the space cannon is defending all of them at once right like the
the pds to just makes it a thing nobody can touch uh so it's it's just it's very very good you also
are making money handover fist and you absolutely can just save trade goods all game long and set up
well for economy objectives the stage to spend 16 spend 10 trade goods all of that is always easily
in your grasp you're not usually scoring those e-cons with like planets alone you're not a big go
take a bunch of slices factions necessarily uh but you can just have money sitting there and as
long as economic equality doesn't crush your dreams you'll you'll be able to ride that into the end
game uh control objective specifically is where things can get tricky but not always uh it's just a
matter of we're not so great at the ground game um we should have tech that gives us access to the
board it's just a matter of did do our opponents have uh like the defenses to do it right not only do
you have to take stuff you have to hold it for the whole round and so that involves stalling long
enough to go late and you know there's other factions that are better at you than waiting things out
and then doing all the control objectives a sorrow no mad mahaq there's tons of factions that can
just you're not gonna beat them in control sorry in in most cases you'll hold on to like your little
corner right you'll you'll hold on to like three of your systems with ease it's the getting all that
extra other stuff that is that's trickier and is honestly the reason why like all game long you need
to be playing it kind of easy on just like let's just score objectives we don't need to go out of
our way to do anything crazy let's build up like a really huge critical supply of plastic so that
then again we have more stuff than other people to go take what we need to take we we need to be in
the late game having the highest number of plastic out there that's hard to do with some factions
but like you need to be up in the running of like just the most stuff to go take things that's that's
part of being an econ faction right is I spent more money on plastic than you did which means my
plastic can crush your plastic right and that's kind of what you're aiming for um but our biggest
oh secrets are a breeze uh we'll just throw that out there you can do all of them especially the
action phase ones that people struggle with anti fighter brought like scoring the last hit with
anti fighter barrage bombardment uh turn north leads to dust those are those are like way easier for you
than very grass everybody else in the game yep uh all of the secrets are doable for you um but our biggest
limitation to all of this is just that we don't have a superpower like we we are solid we have a
good like bedrock to do all of these things but we don't have a quantum data hub node trick we don't
have a cavalry or a nomad parade we don't have as saw installing things out there's just nothing
fancy and we're relatively disliked most of the game people will overlook their displeasure for
us for the cookies we can offer them but we don't just like get a bunch of like really cozy
favors I would say generally speaking like like like the extra cozy favors like when sardak and
mentak are next to each other and they're just like hey let's just like really make this work for
each other because there's no reason to drag each other down I don't think you get those kinds of
relationships as jolnar um we win by staying in the pack and then locking up speaker order to score
the stage two or we got an imperial point somewhere in the late game but that speaker order we
talked about earlier is definitely like a huge consideration because we just we don't have some
other way to like snipe the win from the claws of defeat or whatever like we we have to we have to
like find a solid path into the win I you just don't see jolnar wins very often that are a big surprise
it's usually around five is like jolnar's the problem and let's see if the table can deal with
that problem and you made it through it or not you had you short up enough defenses to to score
those points or you didn't uh and that's kind of how the games peter out in that way sometimes
they're a boring faction they're a boring good faction because it's just like you kind of wipe
your hands of the game towards the end of it where you're like listen I I win on the two or I don't
I I don't have much else to contribute here all attempt one little win slay over there with my pockets
of dreads but beyond that I don't have the stuff to go do stuff yeah yeah it's funny because I feel
like I feel like you make this point with almost every faction that you write as my guide for
at every single time you'll be like we're hated we're like dislike because it's and it's sometimes
will be because they're so good or because they're annoying to other players but you always you
at almost every single time you make a point where you're like yeah we're we're people hate us you
know we're just disliked I don't know how to just have that collouin charm that puts you in the
running every single game without fail like I don't know how to do that you know where collouin can
play almost any faction actually that's not your collouin just plays a sorrow all the time and wins
like a sorrow in my hawk right I don't know I'm throwing completely unnecessary shade he just won
today as a sorrow so yeah yeah well I mean yeah I mean I think that maybe part of it is that collouin
isn't on a podcast like talking smack about you right now you know what I mean like that might be
part of it might be that might be like a good way to start would be to not call out people that you
play with and go I think I think a better like do I just need to disappear into the shadows for
six months and come back and fat fartons is here to play Twilight Imperium and nobody knows what
that guy's all about let's just let him do his own thing and and and see how you know see how good
he is a Twilight Imperium he's like a no he's like you're you're weird open my comedian persona
that you're debuting like you're trashy like 80s comedian persona what's up laugh him up some fat
fartons yeah look at my big shoot okay big suit all right that's kind of a twist
comedienne fat fart yeah yeah doing a reference to the talking heads movie all right yeah
oh yeah that's cool yeah your stop stop making farts that's the name of your first album stop